uh sorry today is dupi means fourth day
of the sixth month and this is the day
that Lord Buddha first turned the wheel
of the D
Dharma
um and I don't know if you know the
story most of it it's actually the first
class I ever
taught uh in New York it was about
uh over 20 years ago let's say and uh we
studied the Golden Light Sutra which is
famous in Mongolia and uh one of the big
scenes in that is taluan which means
when the T when Lord Buddha in one of
his former lives gave his body to the
Tigers and her Cubs four four Cubs and
then he prayed that in the future when
he was reborn that those would five
would be his first disciples uh when he
first turned the wheel and then they
were the the Cubs and the mother were
reborn as
um uh called daa which are the five
first disciples who were originally
yogis Hindu yogis with him and they were
practicing aestheticism like burning
themselves or or um staying out in the
sun or uh doing weird things like poking
themselves with sticks and and as a
method for enlightenment and then um
Lord Buddha got tired of that and said
I'm going to try a different way and
then he sat under the bodh tree in
bodaya and you know got enlightened and
then I guess I don't remember how long
it was but for months he didn't uh teach
he just stayed in the forest and he said
nobody can get it you know he was kind
of uh discouraged and he thought that no
one would be able to understand what he
had to teach and then finally you know
he goes to vasi to the Deer Park in s
beris and um teaches very close to
binaris and turns the wheel of the
Dharma for the first time and teaches
what mainly
yeah the four Arya truths okay in the
first turning of the wheel so you know
people all over the world um they
celebrate Sagwa a lot when Lord Buddha
was
born but to me this is the holiest day
of the year you know to me this is the
greatest day of the year uh it's one
thing to put your body in the world it's
another thing to put your teachings in
the world you know and uh to me uh
putting the teachings in the world is
much more worthy of uh commemoration you
know and
uh also it's very custom much accustomed
to do big puas and put out big offerings
and um you know and uh pray all day long
and stuff like that and uh personally
that just seems to me often I mean when
I've been there and I enjoy prayers but
even for me it gets long I read his
Holiness biography he said he used to be
looking at the cup and wondering when
the break would be and uh
and and to me
um there's also a distinction in Tantra
as you get higher in Tantra there's less
and less uh emphasis on physical ritual
and more and more emphasis on inner
ritual and uh and so uh and mean that's
what distinguishes in one school the
four tantric classes from each other uh
less and less on the outside more and
more done on the with the body and with
the inside um
so to me the neatest thing to do on
today is to uh teach Dharma and have a
class and that's the offering you see to
me that's a billions of times holier
than um making a bunch of Pancakes and
offering them on the Altar and stuff
like that I mean offer the class on the
altar offer the the understanding and
the wisdom on the Altar and and it's
always been my way and I have a feeling
that diamond mountain is going to be I
have a feeling we're just going to be
less I think what distinguish just ACI
in general from many groups is that the
emphasis on on offering your knowledge
and your understanding and and your
practice uh and less emphasis on um on
outer uh physical kinds of uh you know
uh buildings or temples or you know to
me if ACI never gets bigger or diamond
mountain than than people sitting in
Winston's living room taking classes
then that's okay with me you know like
buildings just need more I mean we got
to have some buildings as we'll soon
find out but um but generally uh it's
the knowledge passing from living PE
person to living person to me which is
the offering um so today I don't know
it's just coincidence I guess but we are
entering today the greatest part of the
utar Tantra the holiest part um which is
about come right
Tatu uh
sh sugat the seed of Buddha in inside
you the seed of Buddha and that's really
you know what most people think of when
they think of the utar tanter when you
debate in the monastery and when utar
tant comes up I don't know 80% of the
time it's in connection with inner
Buddha you know the Buddha seed within
you and so I thought to dedicate um a
lot of classes to this particular
subject and it kind of works out nice
cuz this in August we have three utar
Tanto classes and we finished two more I
think just before the October teaching
in tuon uh but I figured to devote these
three to to come to datu to uh the
Buddha seed inside of us you know Buddha
nature and uh and I I thought to do it
in the following way
um first of all there's a very long
section in utar Tantra that we're going
to cover today called the nine images
these are nine different images about
how Buddha nature is within you and how
it's concealed from from us so how we
have a Buddha nature but how it's
concealed by certain things and we can't
see it and then working to remove those
obstacles those obscurations and then we
can reveal Buddha nature
um so and there's going to be a lot of
images like uh the first one is
a little buddha image hidden within a a
closed lotus flower so if you've ever
seen a a Lotus as they open the petals
are not that soft they're more like
um aroke aroke yeah a lot like that they
feel like that they're not like uh like
Silk or anything they're more hard and
then uh they when they're closed you
can't get them open uh and then finally
when they open you find out you know
there's beautiful things inside and and
the if you know the Padma Samba right
which means uh P which means who was
born out of the lotus and they say like
Virgin Mary's Immaculate Conception that
Holy beings can take different kinds of
uh miraculous birth and parasa is
thought many holing being are thought to
come out of lotus flowers like a lotus
flower opens and then this holy this
tiny little creatures there and then um
grows into a full person like you heard
the story of patan jali
patali fell in the water right uh in in
his mother's CED hands and then this
being just pops forth so um the idea is
that uh Buddha is is within you and then
when the Lotus opens you can see oh
Buddha was there you know um so they're
going to be nine images like that today
but there's a certain danger to those
images there's a big danger to those
images which is the idea
uh what's inside you know what is it
that's revealed is it Buddha or is it
Buddha
nature you see what is hidden from us is
it a finished Buddha because all of
these images are going to be like oh
there was a all along there was a little
Buddha statue inside this flower and
then the flower open and oh we see this
little beautiful little Buddha statue so
you can imagine that over the centuries
there's been this problem uh people took
a to mean that there's a Buddha inside
of you already and you just have to
uncover it you know that somehow you are
already fully enlightened inside and you
just have to uncover it and if you read
the utar Tantra and you go through the
nine images for Buddha seed Buddha
nature they are all in the form of like
something that opens and then you see
something inside that was there all
along but it's but Buddha nature is
different from Buddha right Buddha
nature is the seed for a Buddha in fact
we said that Buddhist don't have Buddha
Buddha nature yeah well it already grew
into them right so uh but through the
centuries there's been this problem has
popped up that people have interpreted
Buddha nature to be
Buddha somehow like a positive thing
like in our lineage in our direct
lineage like we understand that what Aya
means is that the capacity for
buddhahood and especially the space for
buddhahood to happen which means what
emptiness emptiness your Emptiness is
like the space for Buddah Hood to happen
that's inside the Lotus but it wouldn't
make a very good image would it I mean
you open it up and there's nothing near
you know what I mean so I is or M is
like saying okay there's a little Buddha
statue there but then over the centuries
people have gotten confused and taken it
to be an actual finished Buddha inside
of you already okay now there's
different
there's a there's a reason why that
would be useful and there's a reason why
that would be harmful to think that like
if you didn't understand emptiness very
well it might be more useful for you to
tell your disciples oh you have a Buddha
inside of you we just have to reveal it
you know then if the person is more
sophisticated and they've been through
ACI courses and all that you could say
look you have an emptiness inside of you
and that allows you to become a Buddha
and that's what this little statue
represents so why I brought that up is
that we're going to have three classes
this month on on
S right the Buddha nature we're going to
have three classes first class is the
nine images from ay mraa work the second
one we're going to go through the Sarah
May monastic text presentation of Buddha
nature which is very detailed and very
cool and very correct you know like
really cool and I'm still trying to
decide I haven't I haven't picked the
text yet we can choose either
Kar who's the main textbook writer
forame he lived about four or 500 years
ago or we could take Chon D has a nice
uh section on it like 20 pages on it uh
and of course he wrote The Diamond
Cutter commentary that we study so he's
the secondary textbook writer for C so
I'm kind of like seeing which one I kind
of like hi Demag because he has a debate
about a lot about the mind only
schools ideas about Buddha nature and I
like chy d because he's and he's more
he's a amdo he's more he's more Western
in his presentation so I'm kind of or
maybe I'll mix them together or
something I don't know uh but uh that'll
be the second one and then I thought for
the third one there are a lot there's a
very big school in Tibet that grew up
over 700 years time called
januma uh and this is like a kagu uh
influence but it also has nma uh
influence and sometimes gupa influence
and sometimes what we call REM which is
called non-aligned Su the SE non-sex
sect uh uh school but it was it was a
synthesis of all these ideas and they
were pretty strong in Tibet and a lot of
the llamas you'll meet in the world
nowadays who are not galupa are are are
whether they how well they can express
it or not they are jba by tradition uh
their viewpoints are the emptiness
version that was taught in the 13th
century by a certain llama from a place
called jonang and then was carried on in
Tibet up to the present time and
especially strong in in a llama named
jamong K and we're studying jamun
because he's he's good he's got some
good uh presentations of the inner body
the chakras the channels and things like
that so actually some of us have been
working on on that text and it will form
part of the tantric series and I'll
describe that in Tiger Rider weekend I
think next weekend
um but there presentation on Emptiness
is wrong and the presentation of Buddha
nature is
wrong uh The Emptiness teaching they
give is called
shenton uh it's called emptiness of
something else and um we touched on it a
little bit back in New York during the
ACI classes do you know which on was it
uh body SAR I think
uh jeta criticizes this uh version of
emptiness and we spoke about it very
briefly and I remember afterwards some
guy came up to me and said I'm leaving
class you know and I said why and he
said because you're dissing shentong you
know and my my root Lum believes in
shentong you know so like at the time I
was like why don't you just stay in
class and debate with me and he said n
I'm just going you know and he left for
good and then I thought it felt bad
because
um I felt like I should have presented
shentong uh that kind of
emptiness uh more more thoroughly and
then described why it was mistaken more
thoroughly and then maybe they wouldn't
have that problem but I didn't know that
much about shentong except for what
Jessa complains
about so what I wanted to do for the
third class this month I got a nice root
text on shentong by the greatest master
shentong and I'd like to teach you that
I'd like to go through that with you and
then we have in saon n
which is another text by the same Master
jamun we have their version of uh Buddha
nature which is based on a mistaken
understanding of the utar Tantra you see
and I thought it's really good to go
through those two mistakes because
they're intertwined the idea of what
emptiness is and the mistake about what
Buddha nature is both come from these
nine images that you're going to get
today you know ultimately they all
derive from the mistake that oh you open
the flower and there's something in
there it's not just emptiness there's a
Buddha in there and then this whole idea
about what emptiness is and things like
that you can kind of historically see
the threads going back to the entire
Tantra so I thought it'd be really nice
to have a whole reading uh of the
original text of that school and also
containing original readings from them
about uh Buddha nature because if you
read their book on Buddha nature which
we did in s nun when they get to our
version of emptiness it's one line long
and it says and some weirdos think that
emptiness is something
negative that's all they say about about
the's version of emptiness you know I
mean what we call the G version
emptiness and I'm afraid that when you
get to the Glo presentation of shenton
you might see the same mistake meaning
oh some weirdos say that emptiness is
blah blah and then they just go on and
you don't get to hear the other side
really make their case so I thought it'd
be cool to let the other side make their
case in a detailed way and then I think
it can sharpen your understanding of
emptiness and it sharpens your
understanding of Buddha nature because
what you'll get when you teach it in
Tucson in October is you'll get the
same the same uh ideas come up in
people's minds automatically you know
emptiness is a black hole emptiness if I
took this wall away that would be
emptiness you know empty ESS is of the
wall is everything other than the wall
if you remove the wall that would be
emptiness you see or Buddha nature is
revealing like I like to think of it as
a banana peel is probably the closest
thing in in the western world is the
banana inside you know like there's
something substantial inside that if you
could just remove the obscurations you'd
find out that you're just a Buddha
inside and you hear that a lot you know
um it's sort of true and it's sort of
not true and it's good to know why um so
I thought the third class could be a
straight presentation from the horse's
mouth of the other idea which you'll
understand is
mistaken from the second class which is
the monastic presentation uh you know
straight nagaj presentation galupa
presentation and then if the first class
is about the images that cause the
problem in the first place then you'll
have a real nice uh progression images
that cause the problem in the first
place uh why Buddha nature really is
emptiness itself and then why other
people got confused and thought that
Buddha nature or emptiness was something
else and not negative for example it's
not an absence of something okay so we
got to get through the nine images today
and it's being a holiday what I thought
was uh I don't know if you had any plans
but I thought to just invite everybody
for dinner who can stay for dinner uh if
you make dinner okay so that's up to you
you know I think there's lots of food in
there that you could improvise we didn't
buy anything specially like you know
there's lots of Cheerios and ice cream I
mean that would be my idea of a have a
good dinner but
uh but you know there's like rise and I
don't know whenever you can make
something you know and then you know we
can hang out and have dinner together
after uh after class you know um so you
know anybody who wants to stay and help
do that that's cool anybody want to be
in charge of that dinner just so there's
a boss no I'll be in you sure okay okay
well you decide uh you look around
during the break today and see what's
edible and I don't know like the pizza
from the day we got out of retreat is
probably a little old
nothing but uh you know there you see
what's in there I yeah okay uh so I
thought it'd be cool to do that okay
we'll
start I tried to finish the readings I'm
sorry I didn't get them yet there two
two and a half are
translated uh you might get the first
one printed out on Wednesday okay and
maybe the second one uh but this time
we're putting in Sanskrit and it's a
little gets a little more complicated to
to do all the conversions and stuff and
we're not used we're not really used to
it yet we haven't really we figured it
out but it's a little slow
okay okay hey here's the first of the
nine images for Buddha nature okay for K
right how do we get to K first we
did
Buddha yeah so and then come right round
to come right uh what is the seed inside
of us that creates all those good things
okay so nine images here's the first one
okay can you see me
good good good
morning what's that mean okay yeah
yeah you guys are have fun I thought
that uh we should
start we should start speaking a little
Tibetan around here and maybe Sanskrit I
maybe eventually by September 04 I'd
like to just be doing a lot of the
normal conversation in tibetan and
Sanskrit you know what you do at first
is you just replace words like gesi lar
would do with you and S you know so he'd
say you know it's not really necessary
to good because it's no good to carve it
and then you you just have one toet
syllable in there and then you you start
to expand it from there and then you
just naturally start to understand more
and more say
s bang LA s means
Buddha stands for
p i mean if you really wrote the whole
thing out it would look like
this okay I mean this would be connected
here it would look like
this in a
book and that's Padma that's the Tibetan
way of squishing the the two syllables
together badma like when you say it's a
corruption
ofma okay
and the Mongolians say BMA so you see a
lot of Mongolians Nam badma
okay means uh lousy bad stinky
rotten okay it's kind of weird for
a budma right for a Lotus La Means
inside okay and there's we'll do the
Sanskrit for each of these you you'll do
it with chrisy LA on Wednesday okay
coming up oh sorry next Saturday no
uh we'll have to figure it out a time
it's not going to be in October I think
you better cover it before then but
we'll talk about it um because next
Saturday we're booked but um it means
but there we have the Sanskrit this is
all taken directly from the Sanskrit
verse from thear Tantra um this is the
translation inban so a Buddha inside of
inside of a rotten Lotus closed shut
closed right but the point is that the
Lotus is somehow old got old like it
never opened properly and it smells bad
and the petals are starting to get brown
you know and U so it's called like a and
and it's a ugly Lotus
okay now in all of these images we're
going to have uh different levels right
first we're going to have the what you
can call the I I think the most
important part is the obs obscuration
or I don't know what you want to call it
the cover or the the veil you know how
do you spell it
v v Veil The
Veil The Veil that covers the Buddha
nature okay so in each of these
nine uh images there's going to be
something bad that's covering the real
thing so inside the lotus flower is this
tiny little buddha image and you have
the feeling that if it opened up then
the Buddha would pop out and then
suddenly they just grow full size you
know like that how pangel was born and
things like
that so this idea of a veil so first
we're going to have an idea of a veil
then there's going to be the
idea a special angle of the Buddha
nature in each of the nine like the
Buddha nature looked at from a slightly
different angle so you can say Veil you
got to remind me to cover each one then
there's an
angle uh is that angle on the on the
Buddha nature right
and then there's going to be some uh
clue about uh removing the
veil so we'll start with this
one galop J says that each of the nine
images is talking about the veil in a
slightly different whale a slightly
different Veil so he says that the
reason there are nine images and these
are very famous images I should tell you
from a book
called It's a Sutra called the essence
of the Buddha or the sugat garma so
these are all coming from an ancient uh
Sutra which in my mind brings up a
problem you know or maybe a question if
you read ARA commentary on utar
Tantra a lot of it is chunks of other
sutras you know but who taught those
other
sutras
gatama but where did AAS get the utar
Tantra M Buddha so why does mrea Buddha
go through the trouble of taking Gama
Buddha images and presenting them and
why does he just come up with his own
images you know like if you're a scholar
you could probably argue about that but
I don't know anyway uh it's often like
that of of Parts huge parts of the utar
Tanto come from sutras taught by Gala
okay but the veil in this case says
uh says galub J is one of the three
poisons give me the three poisons the
three Critters in the middle of the
Wheel of Life in the right
order the
pig but that's the causal order how
about the the normal um recital order
okay
is that
the yeah
anyway in the when they recite it
although Michael's right as far as how
it occurs marba occurs first right but
uh here's the first one
uh desire which in ACI we prefer to
call liking things ignorantly okay I
still have problems with that desire
thing I mean I'm still talking with
people I went uh uh we we saw many
Dharma groups in the last month and
people are still talking about I
shouldn't have attachment to ice cream
you know and I'm like that's not the
point you know I mean
uh there's an urge for there's an urge
for happiness there's an urge for what
you like that a great thing or else you
wouldn't get enlightened you know
there's an urge to avoid what you don't
like like whether it's eggplant or
seeing beings go to the hell Realms you
know there's an urge to not want to see
those things you know and uh that's a
good thing I mean you should have that
urge if you didn't have that urge I
would I would propose that bodhichitta
is closely linked to those two urges you
know if you don't have the urge to get
something cool if you don't have the
urge to avoid what's unpleasant I don't
see how you can have bodh you know cuz
bodh is just another form of that the
point is that it's faulty right it's
it's it's broken version of that where
you
would hurt someone to get what you want
because you don't understand what you
like you don't understand where it comes
from you know you would push in line to
get the ice cream uh which is certain
evidence that you don't understand that
allowing others to get their ice cream
is how you get your ice cream you see
what I mean then you've got D you know
to me that's obvious you know of course
you should like things I mean if you
don't like buddhahood how you going to
do it if you don't like to see people
get out of trouble how are you going to
do it you know um so anyway D but not in
its manifest form in its what do you
call that latent or there's another word
like sleeping inside of you what would
you say dormant yeah so the Lotus says
sub J in the first image refers to
dormant ignorant liking of things
dormant uh desire as one of the three uh
poisons
okay The Habit within us the potential
within us to have this kind of wrong
desire that would hurt somebody to get
what we want okay that within you is
what the Lotus represents and that veils
what Buddha nature okay which is
basically
what your emptiness yeah which you can
call capacity capacity is a little
tricky though because it starts to shift
towards a positive thing you know I like
the word capacity in The Diamond Cutter
book we used the
potential and then that's why people get
confused after a few hundred years oh
gishi Michael said potential it must be
a positive thing you know and then
that's what happens right um so galop J
says the Lotus is like this because when
you first get a Lotus when you first get
a flower those of you who've ever been
at godo two weeks after a course was
given and the people cleaned up you know
the god really well they moop the floor
they cleaned up the kitchen they washed
the dishes but they forgot one
thing the all the offerings of flowers
like it's very natural people do this so
there's flowers all over the house you
know and then everybody goes away for 3
weeks or something and then they rot you
know and it's this specific smell of a
flower so gab J says look this Lotus is
the same thing you see when you first
get a flower it's so pretty and it's so
fragrant and it's so soft and it's so
beautiful you know but then it always
rots you know like in fact I guess you
could say that the closer it is to
almost its Perfection then the closer it
is to the day of it rotting you know
it's just a few it's a day away from
starting to rot you know so she say
ignorant desires like that like at the
moment that you butt in line at 31
flavor
to get pink bubblegum ice cream before
then it runs out you know not that I
we've ever done that um not that I like
it either but somebody unknown does uh
and
uh at the moment it feels good you know
you get it in your hand you get the ice
cream you start eating everybody else is
still in line you sort of s out the door
and you know it looks like everything
went well you know and uh and that's
like the Lotus at the moment that it's
most fresh and beautiful but then it
goes rotten because then the karma comes
back to you and the next time you go to
31 Flavors they only have 30 flavors and
the one you wanted isn't there anymore
uh because you brought it in line right
and and so that's why that Veil is very
tricky that Veil prevents us from having
the clarity of Mind of seeing our Buddha
nature and it makes sense right if you
went and buted in line because you
didn't understand how ice cream is made
really then that
reinforces your misunderstanding of the
world it one
more uh one more contribution to your
total misunderstanding of the world you
know 0.001% more reinforcement for your
misunder understanding of the world you
know and so then naturally that would
conceal or start to obscure or Veil your
Buddha nature you see so he says that's
that's what's covering Buddha nature and
again this is the latent form that
you're carrying around with you all the
time if you haven't seen emptiness
directly okay the latent form that's
that's sitting there in you nice and
fine um example I think I told it a
thousand times but I was in Hawaii
visiting my brother surfing right uh
when the oil crisis broke out 19 I don't
know 70 something six was it or three
and uh it was really bad in Hawaii
because there wasn't any oil you know
there was less oil than everywhere else
and um I had just been to India and I
was so proud of Americans that they
never fight over things you know like I
had stood in riots to get a cup full of
um kerosene from my stove where I
couldn't eat the next day you know and
there were like a truck would pull into
town and there'd be a riot and you just
end up like like pushing pulling hitting
people to get your cup of kerene you
know and then um I always said Americans
will never do that you know and then I
went back I went home I went to visit my
brother and here people are in line in
the gas thing cutting in front of each
other screaming and people were shooting
each other you know there was actually
instances of people shooting each other
that's where the duchu had been latent
because there wasn't a uh necessity
there wasn't a situation where they
really needed the oil and then this the
moment that the oil wasn't there like
this seed just erupted uh among American
people and you see it now you know we
weren't violent because we didn't need
to be
violent uh because no one ever attacked
us you know and now we get to
demonstrate our ignorance in full power
you know and attack somebody uh because
they attacked us you see and then so it
was latent that anger violence was
latent and now it's now you can see it
it now you can see it wasn't gone it was
just we weren't more civilized than
other people we were just didn't have to
be violent at the moment you know there
was no uh compelling apparent reason to
be violent for the moment
okay so that's that desire I want to
check one more
thing oh and the the angle okay did we
say angle the angle on Buddha nature
here is
that everybody's got it even people in
the hell Realms and Buddhist can see it
inside the Lotus you see so the theme
through all these nine images is going
to be that an enlightened being or a
wise person who who had ACI classes can
see through the veil and see the Buddha
nature inside so even a hell being you
know like Buddhist can even look at a
hell being and see the Buddha nature
hidden within the the hell being and
then um let me see what they talk
about oh and one more angle is
that this particular little buddha
inside the Lotus is supposed to be
particularly pretty like many it's
supposed to be made of like gold and
jewels and the idea is that
um you will be gaining the marks and
signs of a Buddha the2 marks and signs
of a Buddha okay when when it flower
opens up and when your Buddha nature
evolves or is revealed uh you will be
gaining these beautiful marks okay so
like a a Buddha can see your Buddha
nature and be aware of the beautiful
marks that you're going to get okay like
that
what you going to do any other I'll come
to it because it it connects to the
first three images uh respectively okay
um which brings me to the second one uh
oh about revealing it I didn't see
anything special in G sub J but the idea
is that Lord Buddha teaches you or you
attend a class like this and then next
time you're in 31 Flavors in Tucson or
it's even in buy right the the single I
haven't been there I have to go make my
prostrations uh but um the idea is that
uh the next time you're in there because
of this class you just let the other
person go ahead graciously you know and
that is then a little bit more of your
Buddha nature is revealed to you you see
and the idea is that the idea is that uh
by teaching you see that's the big deal
to me about today this holiday you know
Lord Buddha can't uh wave a wand and
take away your suffering Lord Buddha
people always asking me to pray for sick
people pray for dead people come on come
here while you're alive come here while
you're well you know it's it's cement by
then it's pretty hard by then I mean
it's almost impossible to change it by
then uh you know come while you're well
come while you're alive come to
class and and the teaching is the main
help that anyone can give you you know
so that's how the you see through the
Lotus you know you see through your own
latent desires uh you don't act at 31
Flavors next time you go okay all right
uh the second image and we'll come back
to the second of the three poisons cuz
it's going to be the second
[Applause]
image for
say dangala dangala d d dangala dangala
d d d uh dma means a be like a b be okay
what's the other
BR otherwise known as BR because he
go okay
Danga d means uh c means like in dutti
means nectar right this is the C IND
dutti so Dy means honey the Nector of a
dung dma okay so that's a a word for
honey in Sanskrit it's
and came into the English words me in
French for honey and and me for honey
INX Hy based intoxicant uh mous maleus
yeah like that some other things too I
can't remember but anyway oh m in your
in your suu comes from that okay uh so
anyway this is like a a bee now let's go
back to the second of the three poisons
and see if there's a oh oh the obvious
idea is can
you separate the honey from the bee can
you get the honey away from the bee yes
you see that's the but that's the point
of the image you see the image is that
the honey is there and it's sweet and
it's inside their house but you got to
get past the dma to get to it you know
which means you got to be able to
skillfully get the bee away from the
honey in order to get out the honey okay
so the bee here is the veil or the
obscuration and the Honey is
what Rick or come come uh Buddha nature
okay to get out the Buddha nature it's
it's you got to get past the the be
which would relate to which one of the
three poisons now
naturally sh
[Applause]
again it's the dormant form at this
point it's still dormant dormant
what what's sh
hatred is the old way what's the ACI
way disliking things
ignorantly why do I say that you know
I'll give you the reasoning again you
know someone comes in and says I heard
46 llamas call this hatred uh what's it
no desire hatred and ignorance I don't
mind the a yeah aversion give me a break
when's the last time you had a verion I
mean except for eggplant or something
but
um but again the three poisons are
flowing in your blood every second of
the day you're having an actual
experience of the three poisons 10 times
a minute you know something like that I
mean aversion to me means eggplant
desire means a Playboy magazine you
know which might come across your path
every six months or something right I
mean just in the if people know you
don't like eggplant and they you know I
mean you're not going to I mean I went
to a restaurant the other day and they
started to the guy the waiter T tried to
tell me the specials of the and they
started with eggplant I was like you
don't even have to tell me about that
one you know so but that's like aversion
would only come up once in a three
months or something but what we're
talking about is the poisons that are
running in your blood all the time
you're having
them five 10 times a minute okay in a
very subtle form I don't like it's hot
in here you know I if I went outside it
would stop the heat
right you know maybe if you took care of
someone else and ser someone else on
lemonade during the break you wouldn't
have to sit in a room like this in in 6
months you see that's the intelligent
way to not like things dislike things
okay like that big difference and it's
difficult for us because we're
brainwashed into the first way of acting
right you'll be cool if you walk outside
no that doesn't work that way you'll be
cool if you walk out there and get an
lemonade for someone and serve it to
them then you then um these diamond
mountain guys will build a nice
classroom with central air all right
okay before September 04 all right so we
got what's this other stuff here
uh oh a success a skillful beekeeper can
get the honey away from the bees right
like if you're skillful knowledgeable if
you understand Karma and emptiness you
can get past your own tendency to
dislike things in a stupid way and get
to your own Buddha nature which is your
own emptiness you can get then you can
see it you can get it away and the angle
right I promised an angle about the
Buddha nature here is that Roa what's
that mean same
tarasa all taste the same all taste the
same sometimes I call it I translate it
as a single song it's a difficult word
to translate but what it means is that
honey tastes great I mean to most people
most people have the Cara that honey
tastes really good and it all tastes the
same you know you can have French honey
is a little better actually Irish honey
is awesome okay I mean uh mosqu Honey's
pretty cool and subie honey from this
huge Factory in Kansas or something it's
like tastes like I mean if you're a
honey freak you know it's just like
normal but in generally speaking honey
is all taste the same easa and the
Buddha nature in each being is all the
same you see tastes the same if an
enlightened being looked at all the
beings in this room including all the
bugs um they would have the same taste
you see easa one taste it all tastes the
same okay are they different emptinesses
yes do they apply to different beings
yes are they different from each other
in any other way no they are all simply
the absence of anything that was in
self-existent so they all taste the same
everybody has an equal Buddha nature you
know that's a cool thing so that's why
honey is used here says guub J guub J's
comments are really useful because
they're hard to find anywhere else
[Applause]
what
number
three oh yeah let's see if he says
anything I don't think he says anything
again I think it's just generally
teaching teaching of laen
bua yeah they don't say anything special
he does mention like a skillful Yogi
here but he doesn't say anything
special for
you said there was a clue about removing
yeah not on the first two much I mean
just Lord Buddha teaching okay just
studying Buddhism ACI
courses I should say that last thing
like a clue or a Hint it only comes in a
few of them clearly um
[Music]
say this is not the bu that means the
ancient religion of Tibet that's b o n b
b this is BN okay BN means it's a very
rare word that means the husk or shell
around a a plant uh sorry like a a nut
or a seed like the what they call it
around a rice grain of rice the hull
it's like the hull or the husk uh like
that the
chaff
okay that's what bur
means burn means hidden within the hull
or the husk or the chaff is Ningbo
Ningbo means the
essence
okay and it's the idea of something
edible something good to eat hidden
within an inedible covering so naturally
you have to
get the covering off okay and again Lord
Buddha teaches you studying and then
slowly you can remove the cover and
enjoy the essence and the point here is
enjoyment you know the angle on Buddha
nature here is that you can't really
enjoy your Buddha nature you can't have
the Bliss of swimming in your Buddha
nature as long as the husk is still on
it meaning uh in this case especially
referring to a certain mental section
what would that
be yeah
t right back to the three poisons
say so the normal formula I don't know
if we have that in the I think
it's right so means ignorance and
especially the one that triggers the
first two poisons that's why in the
middle of the Wheel of Life in the old
paintings what
it's the rooster yeah the rooster and
come out of the pig the snake in the old
old ones it's a pigeon and a snake
because pigeons like to procreate so
much uh uh coming out of the the mouth
of the pig which represents ignorance
okay so the the rooster or pigeon do and
the snake which we can appreciate around
D Mountain coming out of diog the pig
you know ignorance and again this
ignorance is the dormant form so all
three are dormant the first three images
all refer to these negativities in their
dormant form sleeping inside of us
didn't wake up I mean we have the
Manifest ignorance all the
time uh but we also have the dormant
form all the time okay uh and then it
applies itself normally ignorance is
most active right after an emotional
stress you know like if you if you
haven't slept enough
if you haven't eaten well if you haven't
done your yoga for the day if you
haven't done your meditation for the day
uh if you just had an argument with
somebody then your di is gone from
dormant to active you know like
ignorance is much stronger that's why
they say uh go up on a high building if
you want to look at your ignorance you
know have someone go up and stand at the
edge I'm not advising it okay this is
the old days but you stand at the edge
of a skyscraper and then you have
someone go like this and then you can
watch your teu go from dormant to active
you know it's like you know what I mean
just to
that for you know many people interpret
it as the fear of death which is not
what the point is the point is that
um you all idea that you should be moral
uh and that that would get you out of
this problem is erased at that moment
you know like like pres barita
disappears at that moment there's just
this instinct to to fight you know all
all idea taking a moment to figure out
the real cause of this Karma and
avoiding that karma is just disappears
and then ignorance just goes from
dormant to dominant in your mindstream
at that moment so that's a good exercise
to watch your last shreds of PR par to
disappear from your mind okay or it
could be your favorite ice cream and
then suddenly someone says you can't eat
that something like that okay uh
Sobo I mean like having Jerry Garcia see
in your hand and having someone take it
out of it and then all your uh or a
chocolate milkshake like minutes away 30
seconds away at McDonald's and then
having somebody say you don't need that
you know and
uh and then this thing comes up you know
then ignorance goes from dormant to very
active and then triggers the snake right
so um and again the idea of the angle
here is you can't enjoy the Buddha
nature you can't get to the taste of it
you can't sit there it's I mean some
people I've seen eat whole sunflower
seeds like in baseball like they'll eat
the whole thing and spit it out but um
most people would rather take the shell
off you know it's kind of fun like you
have a choice of buying the sunflower
seeds
unshelled I don't like that I mean it's
not the same hit you know it's like if
you take off the showell and then you
get to the essence the Ningbo and then
you enjoy it and then you feel like you
earned it you know and or it's like a
pistachio in a way like uh R's dog Duma
loves to eat
pistachios and so if you really care for
her you open the pistachio and you give
her the nut you know but otherwise she
doesn't get it she gets a piece of it
and then some is stuck to the shell and
then she gets this shell going to her
and you don't get the same enjoyment for
her without unless take the shell off
okay that's the
idea okay number
[Applause]
four
for for
Sayang
Stang uh mang means not clean a
literally but it's a word for like a
cesspool okay
what's uh celibacy okay like clean clean
line okay and then mang means unclean or
um filthy and in this case it means
assessible N means inside of the sesp
sah means gold and in this case it means
a gold
coin and image here is the guy is
running along the road he has a gold
coin in his hand there's a pond of muck
on the side of the road and um he's
running and then accidentally the coin
falls out of his hand and falls into the
cess pool okay and then like he's not in
the mood to try to go get it and he just
walks on you know okay say it's like a
gold coin laying at the bottom of a
cesspool all right um
and the angle on the on the Buddha
nature here is that if the gold has been
down there for a day or or the Gold's
been down there for a 100 years it
doesn't change like it doesn't get
somehow polluted or corrupted and it's
also not going to melt it's a noble
metal it's not going to like uh
disintegrate the gold coin can sit there
for a thousand years you know uh and
it's not going to get anyhow less gold
or somehow
dirty somehow less pure gold somehow
less 100% gold no matter how long the
veil is there uh the Buddha nature is
just as pure just as unsolid as it ever
was okay and if somebody comes along
they call Hen say
henen means one of the kind of do you
know what it is it's one of the kinds of
uh Clairvoyance it's called the eye of a
dity
and it means that you could see in the
cesso where the coin is like you could
get it out pretty you could just kind of
get your hand in there and get it out
right away you wouldn't have to go
swimming around in it okay uh that's
kind of kind of Clairvoyance where you
can see gold underground and stuff like
that you know so that's an image for a
Buddha who comes and teaches you how to
how to reach down and get to the gold
and not get too dirty in the process
okay um let me
we're talking about a Suess
pool guess what it represents in terms
of a mental fliction or a mental
fliction it's based on what we went
through yeah well it happens to be
manifest all three okay all three mental
poisons all three poisons in their
manifest form like at the moment that
you butt the into the line at at 31
Flavors it's not dormant anymore at the
moment you get angry because they
wouldn't give you the ice cream you know
it's not at the moment that you order an
attack on a country 99% of whose
population never hurt
anybody okay uh that's uh it becomes uh
manifest okay the anger the violence
becomes
manifest and that's filthy that's dirty
that's something uh impure very impure
okay so that's the idea of the of the
fourth image all right we'll do one more
and we'll take a break hang on
[Applause]
say Salah Salam there there Salah
Salah sa means Earth and here it refers
to the floor of a house of a Hut like an
adobe Hut you know the floor of an adobe
Hut like made of Earth uh La Means here
in or under under the floor under the
Earth of a person's H is a d d means uh
a
treasure there's a famous genre of
literature called terma yeah which means
a buried like in the um latterday Saints
the Mormon Church uh they say Joseph
Smith found these books uh that were
hidden somehow yeah and in uh Tibet it's
a very common form of literature that
somebody will find an old book that pmaa
wrote and hid under a rock and uh that's
called a ter now you know what a terma
means it means like a buried treasure
hidden treasure so the idea here is that
there's a guy who's been poor his whole
life and he lives in this crummy little
uh Hut you know and with a dirt floor
but um it happens that you know
centuries ago there was a palace
standing on that ground and a king had
put a inexhaustible treasure you know
like the kind of treasure that when you
start spending it it just gets more and
more and uh it' be nice right
Founders program anyway uh but uh there
would be a treasure under the Earth like
that and the angle here
can you guess what the angle
is about the about the treasure what's
the guy's relationship to the treasure
yeah it's just he doesn't know yeah I'm
not talking about the the kind of veil
right now I'm talking about the the
treasure a it's inexhaustible could
never run out but B he just doesn't know
he's living his whole life spent in
poverty suffering you know bills piling
up outside in his mailbox and he could
just Dig Down 3 4 inches and get this
treasure you know he just doesn't
know that's that's part of it and then
gup J says that there's another angle
here if you think about it the treasure
is not helping him out
either the nature of the treasure is
that it doesn't announce itself you know
it's not like the treasure can knock on
the bottom of the floor and say hey I'm
down here you know just dig a little and
and that's the the the nature of Buddha
nature you know you have it and then
other angle is that you've always had it
you've always had it it's always been
right
there but it's not the kind of thing
that's going to uh knock you on the
shoulder and say look I'm here you know
it's not going to announce itself okay
you need someone from the outside to
come and say look you got this Buddha
nature thing there's this emptiness to
things there's an emptiness to you
Therefore your arm can become mani's arm
you know you need someone to come and
that idea is so weird like we were on
the plane yesterday from New York Five
Hour 4 hours 45-minute flight there's a
guy next to us who's very interested in
yoga see it's a hook right he's a
president of a tech company and he's
like into yoga so he sees Christy's
thing coming up on yoga and Sanskrit and
he's like oh well tell me about it you
know but um but then we tried to talk
about the business idea and that things
are empty and that there and he just
didn't he just it wasn't didn't nothing
clicked you know and what are the odds
of him coming up with it on his own then
you see what I mean like what are the
odds of coming up with the idea that
money is empty therefore the more you
give away the more you're going to get
you know I mean who was the first
caveman who figured that out I have a
theory you know I mean I have a theory a
guy kills a deer you know and then uh he
lives up on the mountain and there's a
lower cave and then one day he he knocks
a deer over this cliff and and the
caveman down below gets the deer body
carcass and then the caveman below eats
it and the caveman above gets down there
too late and it's already eaten and then
the next day three deer come to his door
and and he figures it out you know uh
but that's just my theory uh but I mean
how many of us could figure it out you
know the giving away the very thing you
want is how you get it I mean it's
totally abnormal it's totally against
human nature uh who who could imagine
that you know so it doesn't announce
itself it's not like your Buddha nature
or emptiness is going to declare itself
to you
you need an outside Source normally you
need someone to come up to you not only
tell you but like spend years and years
trying to convince you and and giving
you demonstrations of cases where it
worked and stuff like that and so that's
the idea of the poor man and the and the
treasure under his house let me see if
there's anything
else yeah just that point that it's been
there for time with no beginning and you
didn't know about
it and then you need someone from the
outside to come in and tell you okay